Guide to the Robbins Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Robbins family papers
1719-1850
MS 1169
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
(1 box)
Correspondence, notes, sermons, poems, diaries, and miscellanea of the Robbins family of Branford and Enfield, Connecticut. Philemon Robbins, 1709-1781, a minister, and Ammi Ruhamah Robbins, 1740-1813, are central family members.
Robbins family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the estate of Howard Chandler Robbins, 1942.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
For biographical information, please consult the following citations or visit the repository.
PHILEMON ROBBINS, 1709-1781
Philemon Robbins: B.A., Harvard, 1729; ordained as a minister at Branford, Conn. in 1732 and remained there until his death.
Allibone's Dictionary of Authors, volume 2, page 1815.
Sibley, John Langdon. Harvard Graduates [Biographical sketches of graduates of Harvard university, in Cambridge, Massachusetts]. Volume VIII, pages 616-629.
CHANDLER ROBBINS, 1738-1799
Dexter, F. B. Yale Biographies and Annals. Volume 2, pages 424-428.
AMMI RUHAMAH ROBBINS, 1740-1813
Ammi Ruhamah Robbins: B.A., Yale, 1760; ordained in Litchfield, Conn. in 1761; accepted a chaplaincy during the Revolutionary War; did missionary work in New York and Vermont, 1783, 1794-1796; prepared a number of young men for Yale College.
Dexter, F. B. Yale Biographies and Annals. Volume 2, pages 670-673.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, notes, sermons, poems, diaries, and miscellanea of the Robbins family of Branford and Enfield, Connecticut. Philemon Robbins, 1709-1781, a minister, and Ammi Ruhamah Robbins, 1740-1813, are central family members.
Congregational churches -- Connecticut; Families; Branford (Conn.); Enfield (Conn.: Town); United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783 -- Campaigns; Diaries; Journals (notebooks); Poetry; Sermons; Battell, Joseph, 1774-1841; Morton, Lucretia Parsons, 1789-1862; Parsons, Electra Frary, 1759-1824; Raynolds, Peter, 1700-1768; Robbins, Ammi Ruhamah, 1740-1813; Robbins, Chandler, 1738-1799; Robbins, Elizabeth, 1746-1829; Robbins, Francis Le Baron, 1830-; Robbins, James Watson, b. 1782; Robbins, Peter Gilman, b. 1781; Robbins, Philemon, 1709-1781; Robbins, Sarah Battell; Starr, Peter, 1744-1829; Stent, Samuel; Thomson, Irene Robbins; Robbins family
- Inventory
  - Battell, Sarah (Robbins)
    General note
    See: Folder 24
  - Morton, Lucretia (Parsons) (1789-1862) (Mrs. Daniel Oliver Morton)
    - "Deaths Goshen...", 1803 August-1804 January (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Notes on the life of Mrs. Anthony Whiting, 1812 September 12 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Pittsfield diary, 1814 January 1-May 11 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "An unfortunate Mothers advice to her Daughters", undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "The Heavenly Union", undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Poem (fragment), undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Parsons, Electa (Frary) (1759-1824) (Mrs. Justin Parsons)
    - Diary, 1799 April 4-1816 December 16 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Reynolds, Peter (1700-1768)
    - Notes [on chapel sermons at Harvard?], 1719 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Notes on sermons by Rev. Cotton at Bristol [Mass., later R.I.], 1723-24 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Sermons from Enfield [Mass., later Conn.], 1725-68 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Robbins, Ammi Ruhamah (1740-1813; Y. 1760)
    - Relation of his experiences read in the congregation when he was admitted into full communion, 1757 October 23 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Two ALS to his father, Philemon Robbins, 1757 July 7, September [?] (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Two ALS to his daughter, Sarah (Robbins) Battell, 1793 May 7, 1803 October [?] (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Sermons, 1775-89 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "A brief Journal of some of the more remarkable Events in My Tour to Canada", [1776] March 18-October 31 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Journal of the Rev. Ammi R. Robbins... Northern Campaign of 1776 (published edition of the above journal), 1850 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Western Tour-Journal" diary of missionary tours in Vermont and New York, 1794-96 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Robbins, Chandler (1738-1799; Y. 1756)
    - ALS to his father, Philemon Robbins, 1757 January 14 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - ALS to Peter Starr, 1789 August 24 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - ALS to Governor Sumner, 1799 January 2 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Twelve ALS to his brother, Ammi R. Robbins, 1776-98 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Robbins, Elizabeth (Le Baron) (1746-1829) (Mrs. A.R.)
    - Diary, 1766-76, 1783 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Robbins, Francis Le Baron (1787-) and James Watson Robbins (1782-)
    - ALS to their sister, Sarah (Robbins) Battell, 1801 December 6 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Robbins, James Watson (1782-)
    - ALS to this brother-in-law, Joseph Battell, 1806 March 26 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Robbins, Peter Gilman (1781-)
    - ALS to his uncle, Ammi R. Robbins, 1812 April 8 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Robbins, Philemon (1709-1781; Harvard 1729)
    - Sermons, 1729-1779, undated (Box 1, Folder 16 - 20)
    - Diary, 1730-33 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - "3rd Confession" [enclosed in TLS, 1926 Jan 26, from L.E. de Forest to H.C. Robbins], [1742?] e.c. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Receipts, 1762, 1770 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - ALS to his son, Ammi R. Robbins, 1777 September 26 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence with the First Congregational Society, 1743, 1755 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Robbins, Sarah
    - ALS to her mother, Elizabeth Robbins, 1793 August 4 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Stent, Lieut. Samuel
    - Last will and testament, 1736 September 25 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Thomson, Irene (Robbins)
    - ALS to her niece, Sarah (Robbins) Battell, 1798 October 10 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Congregational Churches in Connecticut. Consociation.
    - "Resolutions of the Cons. respecting ardent spirits", undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Unidentified
    - Sermons, 1722, 1749 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Religious discourse, 1730 December (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - "Lavinia a Pastoral" (poem), undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Needlepoint, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Leather goods -wallet, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Newspaper clipping, 1818 (Box 1, Folder 31)